I'm in seventh grade.
(Sunim) Yes.
I want to seek your advice on school grades,
which all students worry about.
I took an exam yesterday.
I thought I did well, but I didn't.
(Sunim) Yes.
So my parents have now lost their temper.
(Audience Laughter)
(Sunim) They lost what?
They lost their temper.
(Sunim) They lost their temper?
I think so.
Mom got angry and scolded me at home earlier today.
My dad will probably scold me now.
When he does, I get a bit discouraged.
How can I get my parents to calm down?
(Audience Laughter)
So if that's the case...
(Questioner) Yes.
Your parents are acting crazy and getting angry over something
that's not worth getting angry at.
Hence whose loss is it for them to get angry?
(Sunim) Who suffers from getting angry?
I suffer!
(Sunim) No. If your parents are angry,
do you suffer or do your parents suffer?
I suffer, no?
(Sunim) Why would you suffer?
Well, my mom...
(Sunim) Your mom's the one who's angry,
why would you suffer?
Well, because I'm the one
that gets scolded by mom and dad.
When your parents lose their temper,
they aren't doing their proper job as parents.
Hence they get angry and suffer themselves.
They deserve to suffer.
(Sunim) Hence you just watch.
(Audience Laughter)
Well...
There is nothing you did wrong.
You're not a bad daughter, Okay?
(Questioner) Okay.
Doing badly on an exam doesn't make you
a bad daughter.
You should only be scolded
under four conditions.
First, you should not hurt or kill others.
This should never happen, right?
(Questioner) Right.
Do you ever hurt or kill others?
(Questioner) No, I don't.
You don't. That's good.
Secondly, do you ever steal
or take things from others?
(Questioner) No, I don't.
Do you or do you not?
(Questioner) I don't!
Thirdly, do you ever sexually harass
or assault others?
(Questioner) No no, I don't.
Fourth, do you ever lie or deceive others?
(Questioner) I don't.
As long as you don't do these four things,
you're fine. All else is fine.
(Questioner) Okay.
In terms of grades, you can do whatever.
It's fine.
Your grades went down a little this time, right?
(Questioner) Yes, it went down a lot.
It did?
(Sunim) Then you ended up doing a good thing.
(Suni) Why?
(Sunim) Thanks to you,
others in your class have seen grades go up, no?
(Audience Laughter)
Yes or no?
Yes.
There'd be others that have seen improvement
in grades, right?
Would they feel happy or not?
They'd be happy.
That's right. You should feel happy for them
even if it's hard for you.
It's okay.
(Questioner) Okay.
And yet your parents don't even understand
and get angry at you.
Your parents are below average.
Just let them be angry.
It's fine. Sometimes grades drop
even if you've studied hard.
Sometimes you take an exam well
and grades go up, even if you didn't study.
Generally speaking, if you study hard, grades go up.
If you don't, grades go down.
But it doesn't always happen this way.
In other words, weather is warm in spring,
weather is cold in winter.
But this isn't always the case.
At times, certain spring days can be colder
than winter days.
Certain winter days can be warmer
than spring.
Is it true or not?
(Questioner) It's true.
Grades can go down even if you studied hard.
Grades can go up even if you played hard.
There are such ups and downs in life.
Do you understand?
Yes.
Hence you shouldn't put too much thought into it.
Don't fret over your grades.
Just do your best with studying.
Scores are bound to fluctuate.
Hence there's no need to be happy
when it goes up, no need to get sad
when it goes down.
Why? Your hard work doesn't go to waste.
Lower grades don't mean that your ability has gone to waste.
High grades don't mean that your ability has increased.
Your ability is yours as is.
It is only grades that fluctuate.
I'll give you an example of mine.
When I was in seventh grade, I took finals in October.
I used to get 90%, and yet I got 80% and grades dropped,
putting me behind three to four classmates.
Would my life have changed,
had I not dropped three or four in ranking?
Or would such up and downs
not matter from life's standpoint?
(Questioner) Hmm...
If you don't know the answer, turn around
and look at the audience behind you.
Let's all think about this.
You're in seventh grade, your final exam grades went up
or down by 10 points.
Would this affect your life for the better or for worse?
Or do grades naturally fluctuate
and have meagre influence over your life?
Those that think it has no influence, raise your hand.
(Questioner) Wow...
Put your hands down.
Do you get it?
Do you understand?
(Questioner) I do!
Do grades matter or not?
(Questioner) They don't!
You're right. You can do better on your next exam.
Even if you don't get a better score
next time, it's still fine.
(Audience Laughter)
Don't be too bothered by that.
Just study hard and do your best.
Grades go up and down.
Think about it this way.
Let's say we take top performers from
30 schools and create a class.
Will there be a lowest performer or not?
(Questioner) There will be.
Let's say we create a class out of
the lowest performers across 30 schools.
Will there be a top performer or not?
(Questioner) There will be.
You're right.
Rankings are not all that important.
Do you understand?
What's important is that you're studying
something you need.
The assessment of it isn't all that important.
And yet your parents aren't getting it.
(Audience Laughter)
Even if you're crying over your grades going down,
your mom should be the one patting you
on your back saying "It's OK.
Long ago, I also got sad for bad grades.
But it wasn't a big deal now that I see it."
Parents should say, "It's OK, as long as you do your best."
And yet they're acting childish themselves.
(Questioner & Audience Laughter)
Don't listen to them and just smile,
since they're being childish.
If they get really angry, just smile.
They're upset for your sake, are they not?
(Questioner) Yes.
They don't mean you harm, you know this?
Just smile and say,
"I'm sorry, mom and dad."
And don't worry too much about it. Okay?
(Questioner) Okay!
Okay, then.